<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>gambi_abo</title>
  
  <subtitle>DIY game controllers with no strings attached.</subtitle>
  <link href="/gambi_abo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/"/>
  <updated>2018-04-19T00:07:59.080Z</updated>
  <id>https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Enric Llagostera</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>GambiCon03</title>
    <link href="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/2018-04-09-gambicon03/"/>
    <id>https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/2018-04-09-gambicon03/</id>
    <published>2018-04-09T15:56:49.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T00:07:59.080Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class="lead"> Open the borders! Tear down the US-Mexico wall with <strong>GambiCon03</strong> and your jet skateboard.</span></p><p><img src="gambicon03.gif" width="100%"></p><h3 id="What-can-I-play-with-a-GambiCon03"><a href="#What-can-I-play-with-a-GambiCon03" class="headerlink" title="What can I play with a GambiCon03?"></a>What can I play with a GambiCon03?</h3><p>The logic behind the controller is compatible with any game that uses 2 discrete gamepad face buttons. However, the controller was designed specifically for <a href="https://sk8border.github.io/sk8border/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sk8Border</a>, a game created for the <a href="https://itch.io/jam/antifa-game-jam" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Anti-Fascist Game Jam</a> by Leif Halldór Ásgeirsson, <a href="http://uncanard.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marc-André Toupin</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/Benwiley4000" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ben Wiley</a>. In it, you destroy the US-Mexico border wall by skating on it with a jet skateboard.</p><p><a href="https://sk8border.github.io/sk8border/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="sk8border.gif" width="100%"></a></p><h2 id="Do-it-yourself"><a href="#Do-it-yourself" class="headerlink" title="Do-it-yourself"></a>Do-it-yourself</h2><p>Here you can find a full list of materials, diagrams and detailed step-by-step instructions for making your own GambiCon03.</p><p>This controller has two main components: a <strong>skateboard deck</strong> which the player activates wth their feet and two <strong>pedal levers</strong> which are moved by the deck and press the gamepad buttons. You can use any gamepad: I used an XBox 360 controller because I already had one and its compatible with PICO-8, the tool used to make Sk8Border.</p><p><img src="gambicon03_18042018_01.jpg" alt="GambiCon03"></p><h2 id="The-skateboard-deck"><a href="#The-skateboard-deck" class="headerlink" title="The skateboard deck"></a>The skateboard deck</h2><p>This is the top layer which the player will be stepping on. It needs to be as resistant as it is customized!</p><h3 id="Material-amp-equipment-list"><a href="#Material-amp-equipment-list" class="headerlink" title="Material &amp; equipment list"></a>Material &amp; equipment list</h3><ul><li>Large piece of cardboard (enough for 3 rectangles with 20” by 6”)</li><li>Glue</li><li>Box cutter or scissors</li><li>Drawing and painting things!</li></ul><h3 id="Instructions"><a href="#Instructions" class="headerlink" title="Instructions"></a>Instructions</h3><ol><li><p>Measure and cut the board shape. It is a 20” by 6” rectangle. This part needs to be strong and resistant, so it’s better to layer it. The top and bottom layers should have vertical flutes. The middle layer should have horizontal flutes. This means that you need to alternate how you layout the rectangle on your cardboard.</p><p><img src="gambicon03_18042018_08.png" alt="Triple wall skateboard"></p></li><li><p>To layer them, you just apply glue between the layers and press them together. Here I used hot glue for convenience, but white clue is fine too. If you want more tips on how to layer cardboard, check <a href="https://vimeo.com/173307203" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this video from Adaptive Design</a>.</p><p><img src="gambicon03_18042018_06.png" alt="Bottom layer"></p><p><img src="gambicon03_18042018_03.png" alt="Gluing middle layer"></p><p><img src="gambicon03_18042018_02.png" alt="Top layer glued"></p></li><li><p>Customize it!</p></li></ol><h2 id="The-pedals"><a href="#The-pedals" class="headerlink" title="The pedals"></a>The pedals</h2><p><img src="gambicon03_18042018_07.png" alt="Pedals stage"></p><p>The skateboard deck activates the gamepad buttons via two pedals with levers. These need to be carefully placed and angled to get the right pressure from the player’s feet to the gamepad button. These are also a bit fragile, so keep that hot glue gun nearby for repairs.</p><h3 id="Material-amp-equipment-list-1"><a href="#Material-amp-equipment-list-1" class="headerlink" title="Material &amp; equipment list"></a>Material &amp; equipment list</h3><ul><li>Gamepad (compatible with PICO-8)</li><li>2x 12” dowels</li><li>Hot glue</li><li>2x Small cardboard rectangles (5.5” by 3”)</li></ul><h3 id="Instructions-1"><a href="#Instructions-1" class="headerlink" title="Instructions"></a>Instructions</h3><ol><li><p>Position the dowel so that one end is on the gamepad button and the other is touching the ground away from the controller. Try pressing down near the ground-touching end: look for an angle that gives a nice button press and release.</p><p><img src="gambicon03_18042018_09.png" alt="Dowel positions"></p></li><li><p>Put a bead of hot glue on the button-touching end. Wait a bit for the glue to cool slightly and glue it to the gamepad button. Make sure to keep the angle you found.</p><p><img src="gluing.gif" width="100%"></p></li><li><p>Repeat the steps above for the other dowel, trying to find a good angle that creates almost a right angle with the other dowel.</p></li><li><p>Cut two small cardboard rectangles (5.5” by 3”) and position them over the dowels. try to find a position close to the ground-touching end but that gives a good position for button pressing. Try putting it in the ground and pressing it with your feet to test.</p></li><li><p>When you find a working position, put a bead of hot glue on the dowels where they meet the pedals and glue the cardboard to it.</p></li><li><p>Put the controller and pedal on the ground near the computer, place the skateboard deck over the pedals, and destroy that wall!</p><p><img src="using.gif" width="100%"></p></li></ol>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt; Open the borders! Tear down the US-Mexico wall with &lt;strong&gt;GambiCon03&lt;/strong&gt; and your jet skateboard.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="gambicon" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/gambicon/"/>
    
      <category term="do-it-yourself" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/do-it-yourself/"/>
    
      <category term="gamepad" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/gamepad/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>GambiCon02</title>
    <link href="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/2018-04-08-gambicon02/"/>
    <id>https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/2018-04-08-gambicon02/</id>
    <published>2018-04-08T15:27:33.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-12T00:02:08.200Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class="lead"> Why let your computer (plus the people &amp; things that make it possible for you to use it) do all the work? <strong>GambiCon02</strong> lets you bring your physical prowess to your immaterial labor games! </span></p><p><img src="sieve.gif" alt="GambiCon02 in action on a BitCoin mining game."></p><h3 id="What-can-I-play-with-a-GambiCon02"><a href="#What-can-I-play-with-a-GambiCon02" class="headerlink" title="What can I play with a GambiCon02?"></a>What can I play with a GambiCon02?</h3><p>The controller is compatible with any mouse-based game that only uses the left-click button and the cursor. It was designed specifically for immaterial labor games, so maybe go seek your fortune on the free games below:</p><ul><li><a href="https://5mixer.itch.io/downbit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Downbit</a></li><li><a href="https://oldmancharles.itch.io/code-clicker" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Code clicker</a></li><li><a href="https://hubix9.itch.io/bitcoin-digger" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bitcoin digger</a></li></ul><h2 id="Do-it-yourself"><a href="#Do-it-yourself" class="headerlink" title="Do-it-yourself"></a>Do-it-yourself</h2><p>Here you can find a full list of materials, diagrams and detailed step-by-step instructions for making your own GambiCon02.</p><p>This controller has two main components: a <strong>base box</strong> where the computer mouse is held and the <strong>mining sieve</strong> which the player uses to move the cursor and click.</p><p><img src="full.jpg" alt="A GambiCon02."></p><p>You will need a printer for printing out the cut-and-fold diagrams or you can just use them as reference.</p><h2 id="The-base-box"><a href="#The-base-box" class="headerlink" title="The base box"></a>The base box</h2><p><img src="base_box_v2.jpg" alt="Base box example"></p><p>We’ll start by building the base box, which should hold the computer mouse with its sensor facing up. You can repurpose any box with an appropriate size or you can use the <a href="base_box_diagram_v01.pdf">cut-and-fold diagram</a>. The mouse should be slightly raised above the box walls, so that the sensor is fully accessible.</p><h3 id="Materials-amp-equipment-list"><a href="#Materials-amp-equipment-list" class="headerlink" title="Materials &amp; equipment list"></a>Materials &amp; equipment list</h3><ul><li>1x Computer mouse</li><li>1x Medium-sized piece of flat cardboard (at least the size of 2 letter sized pages)</li><li>Duct tape</li><li>Rubber bands</li><li>Box-cutter or scissors</li><li>Wooden stick or dowel</li></ul><h3 id="Instructions"><a href="#Instructions" class="headerlink" title="Instructions"></a>Instructions</h3><p>Below are the steps if you’re making your own box. If you’re repurposing a box, you can skip to step #6.</p><ol><li><p>Print the <a href="base_box_diagram_v01.pdf">base box diagram</a> and glue it to the flat cardboard.</p></li><li><p>Cut the solid lines, including the inside slots marked with a star.</p></li><li><p>Score the fold lines on the opposite side of the cardboard. Lightly use the box-cutter to cut the top-layer of the marked line without going all the way through the cardboard.</p><p><img src="fold_00.jpg" alt="Example of folding a scored line."></p><p><img src="fold_01.jpg" alt="How the cardboard looks after scoring."></p></li><li><p>Fold the different parts and introduce the lips in the slots to fix them together.</p><p><img src="lip_00.jpg" alt="An already cut and folded lip."></p><p><img src="lip_01.jpg" alt="A wall section after introducing the lip into the slot."></p></li><li><p>Use the duct tape to fix the lips to the bottom and sides of the box. We have a box!</p><p><img src="tape_00.jpg" alt="Taping over the lip."></p><p><img src="tape_01.jpg" alt="Reinforced lip."></p><p>Now that we have a basic box, we can prepare it for the computer mouse. The following instructions apply to both repurposed and built boxes.</p></li><li><p>Place a rubber bands across the box, which will be used to hold the mouse closer to the box top and give the click a springy feel. Something like this:</p><p><img src="band_00.jpg" alt="Rubber band placement"></p></li><li><p>Place the mouse over the rubber bands and press it down. Use a duct tape strip to connect the mouse to the side of the boxes, taping over the rubber band. This will reduce friction and make for better use of the mouse sensor.</p><p><img src="band_01.jpg" alt="Mouse position over rubber band"></p><p><img src="duct_00.jpg" alt="Duct tape over rubber band."></p></li><li><p>Use another duct tape strip to connect the mouse and the box walls. The mouse sensor should be parallel to the top of the box, so that the on-screen cursor will move when the sieve is dragged over the sensor.</p><p><img src="duct_01.jpg" alt="Duct tape."></p></li><li><p>Put the dowel or stick on the front of the mouse’s left-button and into the box. The stick will click the mouse when pressed by the sieve. You will need to adjust the angle and position of the stick to get a good feel for the clicking.</p><p><img src="base_box_v2.jpg" alt="Stick placement"></p></li><li><p>We’re almost there. Make two small tape loops to fix the bottom of the box to a desk or other surfaces. This way it won’t move around when you are dragging the sieve over it. Now the base box is ready!</p><p><img src="loops.jpg" alt="Duct tape loops"></p></li></ol><h2 id="Mining-sieve"><a href="#Mining-sieve" class="headerlink" title="Mining sieve"></a>Mining sieve</h2><p><img src="sieve_example.jpg" alt="Mining sieve example"></p><p>The mining sieve holds the rocks. It needs a flat and smooth surface on its bottom side and strong sides. You can also repurpose a pizza box (it is our recommended way of making one) and reinforce it with duct tape. Another option is to use this <a href="mining_sieve_v01.pdf">cut-and-fold diagram</a>.</p><h3 id="Materials-amp-equipment-list-1"><a href="#Materials-amp-equipment-list-1" class="headerlink" title="Materials &amp; equipment list"></a>Materials &amp; equipment list</h3><ul><li>1x large piece of flat cardboard (at least XX per XX / )</li><li>Duct tape</li><li>Rocks!</li><li>School glue</li></ul><h3 id="Instructions-1"><a href="#Instructions-1" class="headerlink" title="Instructions"></a>Instructions</h3><p>Here are the steps in case you’re building the mining sieve from the <a href="mining_sieve_v01.pdf">diagram</a>. If you’re repurposing a pizza box, just make sure to cut its lid off, reinforce its sides with duct tape, and add rocks!</p><ol><li><p>Print the <a href="mining_sieve_v01.pdf">mining sieve diagram</a> and glue it to a large flat cardboard.</p><p><img src="sieve_00.jpg" alt="Diagram glued to cardboard."></p></li><li><p>Cut the solid lines, including the inside slots marked with a star.</p><p><img src="sieve_01.jpg" alt="Cutting the solid lines."></p></li><li><p>Score the fold lines on the opposite side of the cardboard. Lightly use the box-cutter to cut the top-layer of the marked line without going all the way through the cardboard.</p></li><li><p>Fold the different parts and introduce the lips in the slots to fix them together.</p><p><img src="sieve_02.jpg" alt="After folding and slipping the lips lines."></p></li><li><p>Use the duct tape to fix the lips to the side walls of the sieve.</p><p><img src="sieve_03.jpg" alt="Reinforce lips."></p></li><li><p>Make a cross with tape starting from the outside bottom side of the sieve, going over the side wall, all the way to the other side. This will strengthen the bottom of the sieve.</p></li><li><p>Tape a long band that circles all the outside walls of the sieve. By doing this, it will deform much less under the weight of the rocks.</p><p><img src="rocks.jpg" alt="Add the rocks. Note the duct tape reinforcement on the sides."></p></li><li><p>Add the rocks!</p></li></ol>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt; Why let your computer (plus the people &amp;amp; things that make it possible for you to use it) do all the work? &lt;strong
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="gambicon" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/gambicon/"/>
    
      <category term="do-it-yourself" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/do-it-yourself/"/>
    
      <category term="mouse" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/mouse/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>GambiCon01</title>
    <link href="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/2018-04-07-gambicon01/"/>
    <id>https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/2018-04-07-gambicon01/</id>
    <published>2018-04-07T15:45:59.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-11T23:54:16.551Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class="lead">In a car-ruled world, why not drive all the things? <strong>GambiCon01</strong> lets you play games with the glamour of car civilization and its ideology!</span></p><p><img src="wheel.gif" alt="GambiCon01 for sokoban."></p><h3 id="What-can-I-play-with-a-GambiCon01"><a href="#What-can-I-play-with-a-GambiCon01" class="headerlink" title="What can I play with a GambiCon01?"></a>What can I play with a GambiCon01?</h3><p>The controller is compatible with any keyboard game that uses the arrow keys. It was designed specifically for <a href="https://pedro-paiva.itch.io/carrocalipse" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Carrocalipse</a>, a game by <a href="https://pedro-paiva.itch.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pedro Paiva</a> about the ruins of capitalism and a car-ruled world.</p><p><img src="carrocalipse01.gif" alt="Screenshot of Carrocalipse"></p><h2 id="Do-it-yourself"><a href="#Do-it-yourself" class="headerlink" title="Do-it-yourself"></a>Do-it-yourself</h2><p>Here you can find a full list of materials, diagrams and detailed step-by-step instructions for making your own GambiCon01.</p><p>This controller has two main components. First, a <strong>steering wheel and axis</strong>, which extends the box where the keyboard is held and controls the left and right arrow keys. The second component are the <strong>pedals</strong> which the player uses to move the up and down arrow keys.</p><p><img src="gambicon01.jpg" alt="Finished GambiCon01"></p><h2 id="The-steering-wheel-and-axis"><a href="#The-steering-wheel-and-axis" class="headerlink" title="The steering wheel and axis"></a>The steering wheel and axis</h2><p>This part of the GambiCon lets you move sideways in the game by moving your steering wheel, which turns an axis and a U-piece presses the arrow keys. It also has some internal structures that will hold the pedals later on.</p><h3 id="Materials-amp-equipment-list"><a href="#Materials-amp-equipment-list" class="headerlink" title="Materials &amp; equipment list"></a>Materials &amp; equipment list</h3><ul><li>1x large piece of flat cardboard (at least 30 per 30 inches)</li><li>Duct tape</li><li>Box cutter &amp; scissors</li><li>Marker pen</li><li>Computer keyboard (with NumPad)</li></ul><h3 id="Instructions"><a href="#Instructions" class="headerlink" title="Instructions"></a>Instructions</h3><ol><li><p>Repurpose a shoebox (in which your keyboard can fit) or print this <a href="gambicon01-diagram.pdf">cut-and-fold diagram</a>. Cut on the solid lines and fold on the dashed ones. Use duct tape to secure the right side of the box for now.</p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-02_pro.jpg" alt="Taped box with keyboard"></p></li><li><p>Use a straight edge to measure from your left and right arrow keys up on the wall. This measure is very important, as it will determine the width of the steering wheel axis and other structures.</p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-04_pro.jpg" alt="Stright edges on the wall"></p></li><li><p>Prepare a U-shaped piece with middle section with the width of the arrow keys. This piece will be attached to the steering wheel axis later on, so it needs to have equal sides.</p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-05_pro.jpg" alt="U-shaped piece"></p></li><li><p>Use the U-shaped piece to find out the width of your axis. Use the middle section of the U to measure the width of two strips of cardboard that are around 12 inches (30cm) long. You’ll get better results if the corrugation of the cardboard runs parallel to the axis.</p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-08_pro.jpg" alt="U shape as basis for axis pieces"></p></li><li><p>Put the axis pieces in a cross section. Use a marker to trace their intersection in the pieces. Cut half of that intersection away in each.</p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-10_pro.jpg" alt=""></p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-11_pro.jpg" alt=""></p></li><li><p>Assemble the axis by sliding the two pieces together by their ends.</p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-12_pro.jpg" alt="Cross-section assembly"></p></li><li><p>Place it across the box to mark where the walls are relative to the axis, so that the depth of the axis is comfortable on the front and back of the box.</p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-14_pro.jpg" alt="Axis depth marks"></p><p>Use the U-piece to mark the axis where it will be near the arrow keys. This is where you’ll slip the U-piece later.</p></li><li><p>With the U-piece, mark the height of the axis on the box front wall. After marking the front, use the axis to mark where the whole will be on the back.</p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-16_pro.jpg" alt="Marking the front wall hole"></p><p><img src="20180409-gc01_redesign-17_pro.jpg" alt="Marking the back wall"></p></li><li><p>Cut the hole in the walls. After that, we’ll need two side rails to hold the tabs that press the keys in place. They are assembled by gluing 3 pieces of cardboard in parallel.</p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-19_pro.jpg" alt="The three pieces for the side rails."></p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-20_pro.jpg" alt="Putting them together."></p></li><li><p>Attach the side rails across the box with tape. They must be placed in such a way that the slots they form are over the arrow keys.</p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-18_pro.jpg" alt="Side rail position"></p></li><li><p>Cut a large rectangular piece of cardboard to be your steering wheel. Mark the axis section on its center. Then you can cut the slots to fit the axis and attach the wheel to it with tape.</p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-23_pro.jpg" alt="Marking the axis position"></p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-24_pro.jpg" alt="Slots cut"></p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-25_pro.jpg" alt="After fixing it with duct tape"></p></li></ol><h2 id="The-pedals"><a href="#The-pedals" class="headerlink" title="The pedals"></a>The pedals</h2><p>To move forward or backwards, the GambiCon01 uses a pair of foot pedals. They press the keys by pulling one string for each direction in the NumPad. Remember to disable the NumLock key to turn this second set of arrow keys on.</p><h3 id="Materials-amp-equipment-list-1"><a href="#Materials-amp-equipment-list-1" class="headerlink" title="Materials &amp; equipment list"></a>Materials &amp; equipment list</h3><ul><li>3x small pieces of flat cardboard</li><li>Duct tape</li><li>Box cutter &amp; scissors</li><li>Wooden dowel or stick</li><li>String</li></ul><h3 id="Instructions-1"><a href="#Instructions-1" class="headerlink" title="Instructions"></a>Instructions</h3><ol><li><p>Make a whole in the right side of your box near the back side. Pass the dowel or stick through it and through the right side rail. This dowel will serve as a support for the pieces that will press the up and down keys on the NumPad (8 and 2, respectively).</p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-26_pro.jpg" alt="Dowel placement"></p></li><li><p>Prepare the key-pressing pieces. They are basically a small rectangle, long enough to reach the desired key. Punch a hole on the back part of it (for the dowel) and on the front (for the string that will pull it down).</p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-28_pro.jpg" alt="Key-pressing piece parts"></p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-30_pro.jpg" alt="Key-pressing piece placement"></p><p>The smaller piece of cardboard on the image serves to make sure that each of the pedal will activate just the intended key.</p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-34_pro.jpg" alt="Key-pressing piece"></p></li><li><p>Use a rectangle of cardboard for the pedal. Make a small hole on one end to pass the string. To connect the string to the key-pressing piece, you’ll need to make a hole in the front side of the box, below the wheel. Pass the string through the whole and tie it to the key-pressing piece.</p><p><img src="20180410-gc01_redesign-32_pro.jpg" alt="String hole"></p></li></ol>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;In a car-ruled world, why not drive all the things? &lt;strong&gt;GambiCon01&lt;/strong&gt; lets you play games with the glamour o
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="gambicon" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/gambicon/"/>
    
      <category term="do-it-yourself" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/do-it-yourself/"/>
    
      <category term="keyboard" scheme="https://enricllagostera.github.io/gambi_abo/tags/keyboard/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
